<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    

    <title>Bastion's Musings</title>
    <generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll v2.5.2</generator>
		<icon>/bastions-musings/apple-touch-icon-precomposed.png</icon>
    <subtitle>A collection of posts on things I find interesting, from programming to dancing.</subtitle>
    <link href="/bastions-musings/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/bastions-musings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-26T22:47:31-06:00</updated>
    <id>/bastions-musings/</id>
    <author>
			<name></name>
			<uri>/bastions-musings/</uri>
			
		</author>

    
    <entry>
        <title>Depression and Me</title>
        <link href="/bastions-musings/other/depression-and-me/"/>
        <updated>2014-11-26T07:11:40-06:00</updated>
        <id>/bastions-musings/other/depression-and-me</id>
        <author>
					<name></name>
					<uri>/bastions-musings/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post is really hard for me to write, but I feel like it’s a post
that needs to be written. I’ve had a really stressful couple of months, and
it’s brought me to the lowest low I’ve ever been at. The kind of low where
your support network kind of falls apart and you have nowhere to go. However,
I’m on the other side of it now, and I’ve started taking medicine for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to put some of my thoughts and experiences from the past month down in
one place. It was really hard for me to do, and it exposes some things about
me that I’m very uncomfortable exposing, but it’s something I needed to do. I
don’t want to ever feel like that again, and I don’t want anyone else to feel
like that. Not everyone goes through depression the same way, but here’s my
struggle. Maybe it will help others understand and help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: This was forged from pure emotion. It will ramble some and move
tangentially, but I won’t change it. I won’t go back and edit it. I want you
to get the unsanitized version of this so you can get a glimpse into my mind
rather than just what I want you to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Brief History of Me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start off, I’ve never exactly been the happiest
of people. I used to prefer to sit back and make sarcastic jokes about things
rather than participate in them. The two hardest parts of my day are trying to
conjure up a reason to get out of bed in the morning, and coming home to an
empty apartment in the evenings. It’s a tough place to be, but I didn’t think
there was anything I could do about it really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I decided that I was tired of living like this. It wasn’t
fulfilling, it didn’t feel good, and I knew there had to be a better way to do
things. It started gradually, I took up a couple new hobbies (namely dancing,
if you haven’t browsed the rest of my blog) and reconnected with a couple of
old friends. It was an uphill battle, it really was. I thought coming up with
a reason to wake up was hard, coming up with a reason to go out and be with
people was even harder. Still, I pushed through it and tried to meet new
people and do new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently though, about a month ago, things in my life started going terribly
wrong. My grades were bad, I wasn’t making rent, my car started to smoke, one
of my closer friends left me, family drama escalated to ridiculous levels, the
whole nine yards… It put me in a really dark place emotionally, really dark.
I was skipping classes, skipping work, and it took everything I had to not
skip dancing as well. Everything I did stopped feeling enjoyable. It’s like
eating your favorite ice cream, but it tastes like ash in your mouth. You know
you should enjoy it, but for some reason, you just can’t. The harder you try
to enjoy it, the worse it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Darkest Moment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a week ago, I gave up. I just gave up, on myself, on my friends, on
my life, on everything. It was triggered when I woke up at 5:30 in the
morning. I’m not used to waking up early, I’m used to waking up late, so I
thought nothing of it. I just tried to go back to sleep, but I couldn’t.
Instead, I ended up spending the next three hours rolling around in my bed,
thinking about how terrible everything is and how there’s no way to fix it,
switching rapidly between crying hopelessly and trying to not care about
anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in my life, I contemplated killing myself… It’s not
something I would ever do, trust me. Please don’t come crashing through my
door with suicide prevention or anything. I just sat and seriously thought
about it. About the people it would affect, about the people it wouldn’t. I
asked myself how long it would take for various people in my life to find out,
what they might miss about me, and what people it would affect the most. I
don’t even know why I was dwelling on it, it’s like a thought that just comes
into your mind and won’t leave. It’s like when you can’t stop thinking about
how you embarrassed yourself, even from years ago. It just pops in and stays
for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that morning, I had given up on being happy. It felt like it had been so
long since I’d truly felt happy that I wouldn’t feel it again. At the same
time, the suicidal thoughts terrified me in a way that I can’t really explain.
I decided to talk to my doctor about it. I was tired of life, I was tired of
my problems, I was tired of my situation, but mostly I was tired of feeling
shitty all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Diagnosis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My doctor talked to me about my family history, my own feelings and emotions
now and in my past, and a few other things. She diagnosed me with something
called &lt;em&gt;double depression&lt;/em&gt;. Double depression is apparently a toxic mixture of
two types of depression, &lt;em&gt;chronic depression&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;major depression&lt;/em&gt;. Chronic
depression is when you’re depressed for a long time, usually years. WebMD
refers to it as a “veil of sadness”. Major depression is the depression most
people deal with, it’s what happens when things go wrong in your life and you
tumble into a down swing. Major depression happens to a lot of people, it’s
generally worse than chronic depression, but it usually only lasts for a month
or so. My doctor told me I’ve been suffering from chronic depression for a
while, and with the recent stressors in my life I was also going through a
period of major depression. Double depression. What can I say, I don’t do
anything half way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She prescribed me &lt;em&gt;wellbutrin&lt;/em&gt;. Wellbutrin is a common antidepressant that
only affects dopamine and epinephrin, rather than seratonin like other common
antidepressants. Wellbutrin is liked for it’s relative lack of side effects.
The only serious one is that it can increase risk for epileptic seizures.
Considering I’ve never had a seizure, that shouldn’t be a problem for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Upswing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after I started taking the Wellbutrin, I felt better. For the
first time in a long time, I felt motivated. I actually wanted to do things,
specific things, rather than just go with whatever happened. I was able to get
up in the mornings, I was more productive at work, and I was able to pay
better attention in class. It was amazing, I didn’t realize that I could
actually feel this way, that this might be how I’m supposed to feel. It was
like a heavy fog had been lifted, and I’m really thankful for that. I’ve got
back my ambition, my drive, and my hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To end this long rant/diary entry/word vomit, I wanted to say that the best
thing I’ve done for myself in a long time is go talk to my doctor and get on
antidepressants. It’s changed my life in a single week. It’s the reason I have
the courage to write this blog post. Depression is a very personal thing, and
when we’re going through it, it can be hard to talk to anyone else about it.
Even your doctor. I know I felt that way, I didn’t want to talk to my doctor
about it at all. Now I wish I had talked to her sooner. This blog post was
really hard to write, and it opens up some wounds and dark places, but it’s
something I needed to get of my chest. Maybe, just maybe, somewhere down the
road, someone will read this and decide to go talk to their doctor and get the
help they need. Maybe it will help other people understand me a bit better, or
understand depression a bit better and push people they know to find help.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Fifth Week, Viennese Waltz</title>
        <link href="/bastions-musings/dancing/fifth-week-viennese-waltz/"/>
        <updated>2014-10-12T11:12:40-05:00</updated>
        <id>/bastions-musings/dancing/fifth-week-viennese-waltz</id>
        <author>
					<name></name>
					<uri>/bastions-musings/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;Next weekend, the Texas Ballroom club is hosting The Great Waltz, which is
apparently one of their biggest events of the year. They’re going to have a
live orchestra that will be playing a lot of viennese waltz. So, to prepare, I
went to a viennese waltz workshop on Saturday to prepare. Turns out, I’m
pretty terrible at it. It’s a really fast waltz, and I wasn’t prepared for the
speed at all. It’s so fast, it only has seven moves total in the gold
syllabus. We learned all of them, but I was pretty terrible at most of them…
I’ll practice this week, and hopefully I’ll be ready in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More interesting news, I think I’m going to try competing in November. I’m not
sure what I’m going to compete in yet, but I’m planning on going to Dances
with Owls at Rice University. Right now, I’m trying to decide if I want to
compete in newcomer or bronze, and what dances I want to do. My partner is
more familiar with smooth and rhythm, but I’m more familiar with standard and
latin. We’ll talk about it, and I’ll give an update next week. Until then!&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Fourth Week, Foundations and Fun</title>
        <link href="/bastions-musings/dancing/fourth-week-foundations-and-fun/"/>
        <updated>2014-10-03T13:11:40-05:00</updated>
        <id>/bastions-musings/dancing/fourth-week-foundations-and-fun</id>
        <author>
					<name></name>
					<uri>/bastions-musings/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;This week, we ended up doing a lot of review. The reviews were helpful for
waltz and tango, but the other dances I feel like I already understand well
enough that I don’t need to go over the basics too much. It was awesome in
west coast swing though, because we finally went over connection. Some of the
new follows are feeling better to dance with now, which is exciting. I’m also
figuring out who’s better at west coast so I can use my full repertoire of
patterns and learn new ones when I dance with them rather than just going over
the basics. Speaking of west coast, I went to my first practice outside of
ballroom lessons this week. I met up with a friend of mine, Alexander, who was
one of the main forces behind getting me into ballroom. We met up and worked
on some patterns I wanted to learn, namely the basics for nightclub two step
and folds in WCS. I also went to a WCS practice session with some of the TA’s
for a social dance class here on campus, which was awesome. I was nervous the
entire time, but I ended up dancing with one of the TA’s. She said that
everything felt solid and awesome, gave me a few pointers on my whip and sugar
tuck, then she told me to work on rolling through. Other than that, she said
everything was solid and I should try to learn new patterns. So, my next goal
is to add more and more patterns to my WCS and figure out the correct way to
roll through. Here’s to another successful week!&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Third Week, Terrifying Tango</title>
        <link href="/bastions-musings/dancing/third-week-terrifying-tango/"/>
        <updated>2014-09-26T13:11:40-05:00</updated>
        <id>/bastions-musings/dancing/third-week-terrifying-tango</id>
        <author>
					<name></name>
					<uri>/bastions-musings/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;So, I didn’t get a chance to go to waltz or tango the first two weeks, but I
decided to try and jump in on it before it was too late. It was… intense…
Waltz was nice, but I didn’t figure out how to do the basic moves until the
very end of the lesson, and even then I was kind of shaky. Tango was even
worse. Everyone else was focusing on making it look right, while I was
focusing of getting the footwork down. Still, the instructor focused on the
basics and getting them right, so it was bearable. I should find a partner to
practice tango and waltz with so I can get up to speed. Aside from those two
classes, we were making sure we had our basics down and adding a few of the
more iconic moves for each of the dances. Things like the fan in rumba and the
spinning left side pass in west coast swing. It was fun, hopefully I’ll figure
out tango and waltz soon.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Second Week, Basics</title>
        <link href="/bastions-musings/dancing/second-week-basics/"/>
        <updated>2014-09-19T13:11:40-05:00</updated>
        <id>/bastions-musings/dancing/second-week-basics</id>
        <author>
					<name></name>
					<uri>/bastions-musings/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;I was worried that things would slow down too much after free week, but it was
actually very helpful. This week we focused on doing the basics and doing them
right. We went over the things we learned during free week and learned the
correct way to do them. It was nice, and I feel like I have a much more solid
foundation and a better idea on the stylistic difference between the different
dances. I know a decent amount of west coast swing, so I felt like that lesson
in particular was slow, but I know that there are technique things that are
important that I should focus on. I’ll probably use this as an opportunity to
work on leading, leg line, rolling through, and making the dance look right.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Free Week</title>
        <link href="/bastions-musings/dancing/free-week/"/>
        <updated>2014-09-12T13:11:40-05:00</updated>
        <id>/bastions-musings/dancing/free-week</id>
        <author>
					<name></name>
					<uri>/bastions-musings/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;This will be a short post. I went to Texas Ballroom’s free week, and it was
pretty crazy. The room was literally full of people, all of us trying to
figure out how to dance. The lessons were all pretty rushed because the
instructors were trying to get us to something that felt like dancing as
quickly as possible. I’ve been assured several times that there will be less
people next week, we’ll see what happens. I almost went to my first social
dance, but ended up deciding against it at the end. I feel like I should know more
than the basic before I dance socially.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>A Note From The Future</title>
        <link href="/bastions-musings/other/a-note-from-the-future/"/>
        <updated>2014-09-11T08:11:40-05:00</updated>
        <id>/bastions-musings/other/a-note-from-the-future</id>
        <author>
					<name></name>
					<uri>/bastions-musings/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;I decided to take a moment and write out a letter that I hope to craft if I
manage to live until I’m 95. It’s based loosely on the prologue to Bertrand
Russel’s autobiography, which can be found
&lt;a href=&quot;http://users.drew.edu/jlenz/br-prolog.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I wrote it to give myself
a clearer outlook on some of the things I’m going through right now, and as a
way to figure out the kind of person I would like to be as I grow older.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-i-have-lived-for&quot;&gt;What I Have Lived For&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming on my 95th year, I’d like to take a chance and reflect back on my life.
95 is longer than I ever thought I would live, but I’m glad to still be
cognizant enough to be a part of my great grandchildren’s childhoods and write
short letters such as this. When I think back, I can see that my life has
mostly been guided by two things, making others happy and raising my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s really easy to live your life to please only yourself, just doing what
you want when you want to. It’s much harder to try and make others in your
life happy. When I was young and foolish, I tried to make everyone happy, even
complete strangers… With the wisdom of age, I realize now that you can never
make everyone happy, no matter how hard you try. Down that road lies only
depression and regret. Instead of making others happy, I found people that
have truly enriched my life and I’ve done my best to enrich theirs as well.
It’s not about an equal trade, it’s about doing good because it’s the right
thing to do. When you find others who have that same value, it’s easy to grow
together and become the best version of yourself while helping them do the
same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few people in this world are worth sacrificing your own well being for. When
it came down to it, I decided to dedicate myself to my family and close
friends. It was a hard decision to try and have kids and raise a family, but
I’m glad that’s the decision we made. At first, I was hesitant. I had spent so
long trying to avoid the drama of my parents household, I didn’t want to bring
about exactly what I was trying to avoid in my own household. It’s different,
though, being a parent rather than a sibling. There is something magical about
bringing another human being into the world and passing on all of the
knowledge you yourself have learned over the years. I couldn’t be more proud
of my children, my grand children, and the great things they’ve gone on to
accomplish. The opportunities that lay before the generations that came after
me are mind blowing, and I’m glad that we were able to tear down the barriers
that lay before them and let them become such amazing people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many parts of my life that I didn’t understand and that hurt me as I
went through them. Looking back, I realize now that they were simply
challenges for me to overcome, things to help strengthen me into the father I
needed to be and the grandfather I wanted to be. I’ve lived a full life now,
and I can think fondly of it without any regrets.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Street Smarts vs. Book Smarts</title>
        <link href="/bastions-musings/programming/street-smarts-vs-book-smarts/"/>
        <updated>2014-08-14T08:11:40-05:00</updated>
        <id>/bastions-musings/programming/street-smarts-vs-book-smarts</id>
        <author>
					<name></name>
					<uri>/bastions-musings/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;Ever since I started becoming a part of the software development community in
Austin, I’ve heard an argument on street smarts vs. book smarts when it comes
to programming. I’ve been a part of discussions in cafes that went on for
hours about which is more important and which you should really try to focus
on when you’re trying to build products or get a new job. Now that I’m going
into my senior year at the University of Texas here in Austin, this discussion
has actually become very important to me, and a source of inner turmoil as
well. I thought I would take this blog post as a chance to explore the topic
some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Street smarts? Book smarts? What are they even?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, just to make sure we’re on the same page, let’s define what I mean when I
talk about “street smarts” and “book smarts”. Essentially, street smarts
translates to experience while book smarts translates to knowledge. Of course,
the split isn’t that simple and clean, but that’s an easy way to start looking
at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Street smarts is what you learn “in the streets”, or on your job and side
projects. It’s the skill you get when you wrangle code and work with the
frameworks and libraries you use every day. For us at the Frontside, it would
equate to experience working with our favorite technologies like Ember.js,
Karma, Mocha, etc. Book smarts are the more academic side of things. They’re
what you learn at college, from doing research online, or reading books. It’s
a more pragmatic toolset that gives you an idea what your code does behind the
scenes and gives you a collection of generic solutions to common coding
problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, which is better?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the answer to this question is really that they’re both
important. You can get by without one or the other for a while, but eventually
almost every problem needs both to come up with a good solution. If you’re
relying solely on street smarts, if you haven’t encountered the problem or one
like it, you’re gonna have a bad time. Alternatively, if you come at it with
only book smarts, it’s going to be difficult to implement whatever solution
you come up with. You need the context and skill that’s developed with
actually getting your hands dirty and working with the code, but you also want
the pragmatic higher level understanding that comes with researching and
learning about what the code is actually doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you need both, you don’t necessarily need them both equally. I’ve found
that here at the Frontside, it’s mostly been a 90/10 split between street
smarts and book smarts. 90% of the time, the solution is easier to see and
easier to build when you have experience in the framework and with web
development in general. However, 10% of the time, the knowledge from book
smarts finds a better solution faster. Both are important, so you should make
sure to work on getting experience and getting knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But how do I get more “smarts”?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting more street smarts and more book smarts is surprisingly easy. Street
smarts you can get simply by doing your job and paying attention. If you
really want to get more street smarts, you don’t have a job, or you want more
experience in a different industry, then the solution is personal projects.
They don’t have to be amazing applications, they just have to be something.
Playing around with the tools you want to learn is the easiest way to learn
how to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Book smarts require a little bit more effort and motivation, generally. If you
want to get more pragmatic knowledge, the solution is either going to school
or reading. College isn’t the only place to take courses or learn, there are
great online resources such as Code School and MIT’s opencourseware that offer
free or cheap classes for you to learn more. Alternatively, you can spend more
time reading. There are several great programming books available that can be
as general the Foundations of Computer Science, by Alfred Aho and Jeffrey
Ullman, or as specific as Artificial Intellegence: A Modern Approach, by
Stuart Russell and Peter Norvig. If there’s something you want to learn,
chances are there’s a book for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alright, but why is any of this important?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Book smarts and street smarts come into play all the time at work and in
personal projects. For example, recently I was working in a code base that
used the Ruby Sequel adapter for it’s back end. I have very little experience
with the back end, I’m almost entirely a front end guy. We were building a
query, and I knew what I wanted the query to do and look like, but I had no
idea how to build that with the Sequel adapter. If I had more street smarts,
more experience with Sequel, then it would’ve been a simple problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, book smarts can help you tackle larger problems. One of our
current projects uses Backbone for the front end, but we wanted to have
simpler and more versatile routing. One of our developers went and connected
Router.js to our Backbone project to give us the ability to do amazing things
with the router. It’s not something they’ve done before nor is it something
they’ll probably have to do ever again. However, they had enough knowledge of
both Backbone and Router.js to connect them and make them work together,
building a beautiful Frankenstein monster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cultivating both street smarts and book smarts can lead to quicker, simpler
solutions. It can also lead to doing pretty amazing things in your code bases.
While the battle between which is better will rage on for who knows how long,
the best thing you can do is just get better with both of them. Maybe, next
time you have some free time, you should pick up that new functional
programming book your friend’s been talking about and give it a read. What’s
the worst that could happen?&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Being an Apprentice Developer</title>
        <link href="/bastions-musings/programming/being-an-apprentice/"/>
        <updated>2014-07-14T08:11:40-05:00</updated>
        <id>/bastions-musings/programming/being-an-apprentice</id>
        <author>
					<name></name>
					<uri>/bastions-musings/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;So, I used to say that I was an apprentice developer, but I’m really more of
an apprentice human being at this point. I’m still in college, just barely
getting a taste of the real world and the dangers lurking within it. While
many people consider being an apprentice only a stepping stone or maybe
something not to be proud of, I see it as one of the best opportunities of my
life. Being an apprentice, you get unparalleled freedom and a chance to learn
from the best. I wouldn’t trade my apprenticeship for the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who am I anyways?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tell you why I think being an apprentice is so awesome, let me tell you a
bit about myself. Right now, I’m going to UT to get my bachelors in computer
science. My original goal was to get into computer science research, and UT
has given me the terrific opportunity of pursuing that goal and actually
working with robots and trying to deploy them to the new computer science
building. It’s great, and I love most of it, but as time goes on I find myself
yearning more and more to move away from school and into the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This yearning has been added to in no small part by the place that I work
being so incredible. I’m currently an journeyman with The Frontside, I’ve been
working with them for just over a year now. It was kind of a tough choice for
me to apprentice under them to be honest. I met my boss, Charles, at a weekly
meet up one night. Everyone at the meet up was talking and after a killer
recommendation from a good friend of mine I had a time set up to come into the
office and check out The Frontside. When I got there, there were only two
employees in total, and all of us were in a small room in the corner of the
office. It reminded me of a start up atmosphere to be honest, but I loved it.
I loved the people I met, I loved the office, and I loved the work they were
doing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If it was so awesome, why was it tough?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there was one catch, my starting pay was… Let’s just say not ideal. It
was a hard blow when I saw the number, but I could understand it. I was an
apprentice after all. Even if I understood it, I had friends that were already
making 25-30 dollars an hour delivering coffee in big companies. I thought
about it for a bit, and decided that it was stupid to think of the money too
much. I had student loans to cover necessities, and parents to cover
groceries, so I was good. I agreed to the pay because I loved everything else
about the company, and I wanted to learn more than I wanted to make money. I
think that was probably one of the best decisions of my life. Since then, I’ve
leveled up as a developer, I’ve gotten a chance to see the company grow and
even take part in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I honestly think that everyone who wants to be an apprentice
should start at a low pay. If you want money, go intern somewhere. If you want
to learn something, take an apprenticeship and just focus on soaking up as
much knowledge as you can from those around you. I’m especially lucky to be
one of the few employees here, so I get to work hand in hand with some of the
best programmers I know on a daily basis. As an apprentice, you need to
monopolize everyone else’s time as much as you can. Ask them to show you
things, force them to explain it until you truly understand it, even if it’s
frustrating. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why being an apprentice is great&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure you get to hang out and learn from masters, but is that it? No, of course
not. I could hang out with terrific programmers in my free time if it was just
that, being an apprentice is so much more. It’s a chance to make mistakes. In
fact, it’s expected that you make mistakes, which is freeing in a way. When I
came into the office, I’ll be honest, I’d only started working with Ruby a
month previous and had no real experience with it. One of my first projects
was mostly spent breaking things and then asking my boss how to fix them. I
learned so much from that cycle, getting a chance to work with real code is
truly priceless. Now, I’m getting a chance to learn javascript and Ember and
making plenty of new mistakes that I have to learn how to fix, but I’ll be
better for it in the end. my coworkers will be as well. Helping me forces them
to make sure they understand the intricacies of the framework we’re using, so
it’s a win-win most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not the only win-win though. As an apprentice, you shouldn’t just be a
nuisance, bugging everyone about things every few minutes. One of my
coworkers, Brandon, likes to talk about different peoples “value proposition”,
or what they could add to the company. As an apprentice, you have to add
something to the company, not just take away. You should add life to the
company, like an office cat with more potential. You should be able to make
things more interesting, give people fresh eyes to look at old topics, and
generally just be fun to have around. Your value proposition should be making
the office an even more awesome space and helping everyone around you be more
productive than they would be without you, even if it all just boils down to
helping with rubber ducky programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Final Note&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confucius once said, “Choose a job you love, and you will never have to work a
day in your life.” I believe these are words to live by. An apprenticeship
gives you a chance to find what you love and move forward with it. The way the
old guilds work, once you completed your apprenticeship, you became a
journeyman. Journeymen had to find a way to survive off of their craft, they
went from town to town for some amount of time trading work for food and
lodging. While the idea of journeyman may be different now, apprentices
haven’t changed. We’re still here, bumbling about as we learn, trying to
breath new life into old companies.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>